♪Don’t be afraid of long journeys♪
♪不要害怕长途旅行♪
♪Love will comfort your thoughts♪
♪爱会安慰你的思念♪
♪All wounds will scab♪
♪所有的伤口都会结痂♪
♪Become the flower of time♪
♪化作时光之花♪
♪Someone will wipe it off for you♪
♪会有人帮你擦掉的♪
♪Don’t feel alone and keep going♪
♪不要感到孤独，继续前进♪
♪Share your story with time♪
♪与时间分享你的故事♪
♪It will respond with a soft beam♪
♪它会 发出柔和的光束回应♪
♪Hope you can find her in the crowd♪
♪希望你能在人群中找到她♪
♪Be content with a simple life♪
♪满足于简单的生活♪
♪Although life is full of regrets♪
♪虽然人生充满遗憾♪
♪May you always remain enthusiastic♪
♪愿你永远保持热情♪
♪Suitable for every winter and summer♪
♪适合每个冬天和夏天♪
[Love is the panacea] [Episode 5]
[爱是灵丹妙药] [第5集]
[The play is a major literary and artistic support project]
【该剧为重大 文艺扶持工程】
[In Sichuan Province in 2022]
【2022年在四川省】
[Adapted from the Ningmeng language novel "The Healer"]
【改编 自凝梦语言小说《治愈者》】
Come on, something's happening.
快点，有事发生。
General Kouyate is here!
库亚特将军来了！
He had a team of heavily armed soldiers.
他有一支全副武装的士兵队伍。
What's the point? Just two cases of wine?
重点是什么？ 就两箱酒？
Let's go talk to the general.
我们去跟将军谈谈吧。
Average!
一般的！
I lost alcohol. I'll pay for it.
我失去了酒精。我会付钱的。
Please don't cause trouble in the hospital.
请不要 在医院制造麻烦。
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
I will take responsibility for my mistakes .
我会为我的错误承担责任 。
little girl,
小姑娘，
You chose a good place
你选了一个好地方
hide.
隐藏。
Average.
一般的。
Can you speak Chinese?
你会说中文吗？
The general studied at Shijiazhuang Military Academy.
这位将军曾在石家庄军校就读。
He even knows the local dialect.
他甚至还懂得当地方言。
You bad girl!
你这个坏女孩！
Do you know the consequences of selling me fake wine?
你知道卖给我假酒的后果吗？
Fake wine?
假酒？
This is impossible.
这不可能。
I never sell fake wine.
我从不卖假酒。
Maybe you replaced the alcohol yourself
也许你自己换了酒精
and knowingly claimed it was false.
并故意声称这是假的。
As a respected general,
作为一位尊敬的将军，
Do I need to frame you?
我有必要陷害你吗？
You arrogant girl,
你这个傲慢的女孩，
Let's settle the score later.
我们稍后再算账吧。
I'm not here for you
我不是为你而来
But for him.
但对于他来说。
Wait, General,
等等，将军，
You have completed the inspection.
你已经完成了检查。
No tumors or bleeding points.
无肿瘤、无出血点。
How to prove that you are sick?
怎么证明自己有病呢？
My instincts are never wrong.
我的直觉从来不会错。
It's up to him to prove it.
这取决于他来证明这一点。
Generally,
一般的，
Why are you so sure you are sick?
你为什么这么确信 自己有病？
in the past,
在过去，
stand right here,
站在这里，
I could shoot you in the head
我可以朝你的头开枪
When you are standing downstairs.
当你站在楼下的时候。
But now I can't.
但现在我不能了。
This may be due to a decrease in your vision
这可能是由于您的视力下降
Or just because you're getting older.
或者只是因为你变老了。
In any case, you should consult your primary care physician.
无论如何，您应该 咨询您的主治医生。
[Elliot]
[艾略特]
Elliot?
艾略特？
I'm not afraid of death.
我不怕死。
What I'm afraid of is death
我害怕的是死亡
I don’t know who my enemy is.
不知道我的敌人是谁。
Elliot had no guts.
艾略特没有胆量。
And you?
你呢？
if you don't help me
如果你不帮我
Figure out what's wrong with my brain
弄清楚我的大脑出了什么问题
I will kill her.
我会杀了她。
Selling counterfeit alcohol in Lakaya is a serious crime
在拉卡亚销售假酒 是严重犯罪行为
now i doubt
现在我怀疑
It was her fake wine that caused my headache.
是她的假酒 引起了我的头痛。
I'm not selling fake wine.
我没有卖假酒。
Put your gun down.
把你的枪放下。
I can perform surgery on you
我可以给你做手术
but can you believe me
但你能相信我吗
with your life?
与你的生活？
I'm not afraid of bullets.
我不怕子弹。
Not to mention the scalpel.
更不用说手术刀了。
certainly,
当然，
if you dare
如果你敢
take any action,
采取任何行动，
Don't expect to leave the operating table alive.
不要指望 能活着离开手术台。
beautiful.
美好的。
I will perform surgery on you in a month.
一个月后我会给你做手术。
I can
我会
You will definitely find your enemy.
一定能找到你的敌人。
OK I've found the right person.
好的。我找对人了。
You are a good doctor.
你是个好医生。
Are you okay?
你没事儿吧？
Yes, I am fine.
是的，我很好。
Why do you agree with him?
你为什么同意他的观点？
The hospital has examined him.
医院已经给他做了检查，
And it is clearly written on the medical record
并且病历上清楚地写着
There's nothing wrong with him.
他没有任何问题。
or
或者
do you agree with him
你同意他吗
Just to dispel his suspicions?
只是为了打消他的怀疑吗？
Not because of the general's threats
不是因为将军威胁
if you don't
如果你不这样做
He's going to kill me, right?
他会杀了我，对吗？
You can't be that stupid, can you?
你不可能那么傻吧？
I can buy a ticket to leave the country or go to another country,
我可以买票离开这个国家 或者去另一个国家，
Then there was nothing he could do to me.
然后他就对我无能为力了。
PhD. Gu.
博士。顾。
what will you do
你会怎么做
If after surgery,
如果手术后，
Still can't find anything?
你还是找不到任何东西吗？
will be considered
将会被考虑
major medical accident,
重大医疗事故，
You might not even be a doctor anymore.
你甚至可能不再当 医生了。
You can't take such a risk.
你不能冒这样的风险。
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
Are you really worried about me?
你真的很担心我吧？
Absolutely not.
绝对不。
I...
我...
I'm just worried about getting into trouble.
我只是担心 惹上麻烦。
If the operation fails
如果手术失败的话
As a translator I would not be able to escape.
作为一名翻译我将无法逃脱。
wait. Why are you
等待。你为什么
Is this surgery necessary?
一定要做这个手术吗？
Because if I don't someone will die.
因为如果我不这样做就会有人死。
Do you know what happened to the general?
你知道 将军有什么事吗？
I mean,
我是说，
If I don't do this I will die.
如果我不这样做我就会死。
Do you think
你认为
we could have left this room
我们本来可以 离开这个房间
if i don't agree
如果我不同意的话
Operate on him?
给他做手术？
either way.
无论哪种方式。
Why don't you buy a ticket back to China?
你为什么不买一张 回中国的机票呢？
I'll help you delay.
我来帮你拖延时间。
The general cannot return to China.
将军不能回中国了。
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
you do not trust me?
你不信任我？
I believe in science.
我相信科学。
CT scan
CT扫描
and MRI
和核磁共振成像
Both parties confirmed there were no issues.
双方都确认 没有任何问题。
General Kouyate is not sick!
库亚特将军没有病！
Who are you...
你是...
Elliot.
艾略特.
General Kouyate's physician.
库亚特将军的主治医生。
Do you know Chinese?
你懂中文吗？
My grandmother is from Beijing.
我的祖母是北京人。
I learned some from her.
我从她身上学到了一些。
I've heard about you.
我听说过你。
Dr. Gu Yunzheng from Huaren Hospital.
Dr. Gu Yunzheng from Huaren Hospital.
Don't you want zero table mortality records?
您不想要零表死亡率的记录吗？
There is zero mortality at the table.
餐桌死亡率为零。
What a proud record!
这是多么值得骄傲的记录啊！
It shows that Dr. Gu is still too young.
说明顾博士还是太年轻了
And too few surgeries are performed.
并且进行的手术太少。
Newcomers are always eager to prove themselves.
新人总是渴望 证明自己。
I can understand that, Dr. Gu.
我可以理解，顾博士。
But remember, patients are more than just tools
但请记住， 患者不仅仅是工具
Earn fame and wealth for doctors.
为医生赢得名誉和财富。
You are talking nonsense!
你在胡说八道！
In China, Dr. Gu’s
在中国，顾博士的
Weekly outpatient visits and surgeries
每周 门诊量和手术量
Dozens of times more than your French doctors.
比你们法国医生的多几十倍。
From clinical experience,
从临床经验来看，
You are not necessarily better than him.
你不一定比他更好。
is that so?
是这样吗？
How do patients like you understand the clinical experience?
像您这样的患者如何了解 临床经验？
General Kouyate has been a patient of mine.
库亚特将军 一直是我的病人。
The diagnosis result is the result of remote consultation
诊断结果是 远程会诊的结果
Work with a team of French experts.
与法国专家团队合作。
Excuse me,
请问，
Without the diagnosis of a mass,
在没有发现肿块的诊断结果下，
Why did Dr. Gu insist on doing this surgery?
顾医生为何坚持 要做这个手术？
Does it constitute provocation?
是否构成挑衅
Against the French National Hospital?
反对法国国立医院？
Dr. Elliot.
艾略特博士。
your hospital
你的医院
It's not that important to me.
对我来说没那么重要。
I just want to provide
我只想提供
The best treatment for this patient.
对该患者最好的治疗。
Now,
现在，
I am the patient's primary care physician.
我是病人的主治医生。
If you insist on having surgery
如果你坚持要做手术的话
I will invite experts from the Lakaya Health Commission
我会邀请 拉卡亚卫生委员会的专家
to oversee the entire process.
来监督整个过程。
Doctor Gu, I warn you:
顾医生，我警告你：
If confirmed after surgery
如果手术后得到证实
Say you had fake surgery
说你做了假手术
i will sue you
我会起诉你
Until you never get a chance to pick up the scalpel.
直到你再也没有机会 拿起手术刀。
Miss Radical.
激进小姐。
I hope you won't regret it.
我希望你不会后悔。
Damn poker face.
该死的扑克脸。
He has a high nose and is arrogant.
他鼻子高傲，傲慢无礼。
Look no further.
别再找了。
he's gone.
他走了。
He is so handsome.
他太帅了。
As handsome as a Roman statue.
像罗马雕像一样英俊。
What's the use of being handsome?
长得帅有什么用？
The patient has switched to our boss.
病人已经转投我们老板了。
do you know him?
你认识他吗？
He was General Kouyate's physician.
他是库亚特将军的 主治医生。
I asked around.
我四处打听过。
He is the director of neurosurgery at the French National Hospital
他是法国国立医院神经外科主任
He is also Professor of Neurosurgery at the University of Paris VI.
也是 巴黎第六大学神经外科教授。
He can be considered an authority in the field of neurosurgery.
他可以被认为 是神经外科领域的权威。
authority?
权威？
So, who is better, him or Dr. Gu?
那么，他和顾医生谁更好呢？
Well, it's hard to say.
嗯，这很难说。
University of Paris VI
巴黎第六大学
It is the largest scientific and medical institution in France
是法国最大的科学和医疗机构
It is also one of the top five research universities in the world.
也是世界排名前五的研究型大学之一。
Since this authority says that General Kouyat was not ill.
既然这个权威说 库亚特将军没有生病。
Why did he insist on finding the problem?
他为何坚持 要找出问题所在？
I also hope that the boss can find a reason to refuse.
我也希望老板能找到 拒绝的理由。
These people are heavily armed and very dangerous.
这些人全副武装，十分危险。
They are not to be underestimated.
他们不容小觑。
What happens if treatment fails?
如果治疗失败怎么办？
Bullets don't discriminate.
子弹没有歧视。
So what should we do?
那我们该怎么办呢？
Has Dr. Gu changed his mind?
顾医生改变主意了吗？
[doctor's office]
[医生办公室]
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
If my objections are overturned, please join the fight.
如果我的反对意见被驳回，请加入战斗。
Search references
搜索参考资料
guard
守护
Our boss has zero mortality on the operating table.
我们老板在手术台上的零死亡率。
Zero mortality on the operating table?
手术台上零死亡率？
Is this a competition?
这是一场比赛吗？
touching?
感人的？
Maybe it’s competition with myself.
也许这是与自己的竞争。
which doctor
哪位医生
Don’t want zero mortality on the operating table?
不希望 手术台上的死亡率为零？
And you?
你呢？
I?
我？
I have no records.
我没有记录。
Help me find it.
帮我找到它。
I don't have much time.
我的时间不多了。
I must read them all tonight.
今晚我必须读完所有 这些。
This is...
这是...
Very.
非常。
How long will it take both of us to finish?
我们俩需要多长时间才能完成？
Maybe an all-nighter
也许是通宵达旦
It was enough for the two of us.
对我们两个人来说就足够了。
Pulling an all-nighter?
通宵达旦？
never!
决不！
Staying up late gives me acne.
熬夜会让我长痘痘。
beautiful.
美好的。
Let's just do it.
我们就这么做吧。
tell me.
告诉我。
What should I do?
我要做什么？
can you read...
你会读...吗
Surgery records?
手术记录？
What should I focus on?
我应该关注什么？
Excellent...
出色地...
It doesn't matter.
没关系。
Can you understand
你能明白吗
Shadows and lumps in CT scan images?
CT 扫描图像中的阴影和肿块？
Am I useless?
我是不是没用？
of course not.
当然不是。
You have been very helpful to me.
你对我很有帮助。
help me
帮我
Sort these
对这些进行排序
Abstract of thesis.
论文摘要。
I'll tell you how.
我会告诉你怎么做。
Take this for example.
以这个为例。
put with others
和别人放在一起
Are the same,
是相同的，
and put them here,
然后把它们放在这里，
And then this...
然后这个...
[Medical record report, name: Kuyat]
【病历报告，姓名：库亚特】
[Du Yongsong]
[Du Yongsong]
How is this going?
这是怎么回事？
Why did you agree to operate on the patient ?
你为什么同意 给病人做手术
Without knowing the disease?
在不知道病变的情况下？
you are right?
你说对了？
You cannot have this surgery.
你不能进行这个手术。
[Jinhai City]
[Jinhai City]
I have written a letter to Friendship Hospital .
我已经给友谊医院写了一封信 。
They will discuss canceling the surgery with the patient.
他们会与患者讨论 取消手术的事宜。
In what capacity do you order me?
你以什么身份命令我？
director?
导演？
Or my father?
还是我父亲？
No matter what my abilities are,
无论我的能力如何，
I'm doing this for your own good.
我这样做是为了你好。
The patient was a local dignitary.
那个病人是当地的一位达官贵人。
What if something goes wrong during the surgery?
如果手术过程中出现问题怎么办？
ah?
啊？
Do you want to be like your mom?
你想成为像你妈妈那样的人吗？
You don't deserve to talk about her.
你不值得谈论她。
I'll tell you again.
我再告诉你一次。
Listen to me carefully.
仔细听我说。
She abandoned us first.
她先抛弃了我们。
It was you who abandoned her first.
是你先抛弃了她。
we encounter it every day
我们每天都会遇到
various diseases,
各种疾病，
And as a doctor,
而作为一名医生，
The most painful thing is to feel helpless
最痛苦的事就是 感到无助
Face these diseases.
面对这些疾病。
Therefore, I hope that all the students here ,
所以，我希望在座的各位 同学，
I'll never get used to this pain
永远无法习惯这种痛苦
And never give up easily.
并且永不轻易放弃。
Thanks.
谢谢。
OK
好的。
That's it for this class, it's over.
这堂课就这样了，下课了。
Wei'an.
Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Do you like Mr. Gu?
你喜欢顾先生吗？
No.
不。
Don't joke about it.
别拿它开玩笑。
No?
不？
You act enamored.
你表现得很迷恋。
No wonder you kept asking questions in class today.
难怪你 今天在课堂上一直问问题。
Do you want to attract Mr. Gu's attention?
你是想 引起顾先生的注意吗？
No.
不。
When did you start liking him?
你什么时候开始喜欢他的？
The time he helped you when you were late for the final exam,
期末考试你迟到时他帮你的那次，
You've been in love with him ever since, right?
从那时起你就爱上了他，对吗？
I do not like him.
我不喜欢他。
I want to be him.
我想成为他。
Average.
一般的。
I suggest you think twice.
我建议你三思。
You can't play with your life.
你不能拿自己的生命开玩笑。
Average!
一般的！
Madam, you can't go in.
小姐，你不能进去。
[Guizhou Moutai] General.
[Guizhou Moutai] General.
Two boxes of Maotai liquor.
两箱茅台酒。
Double compensation.
双倍补偿。
Is it enough?
够了吗？
If not I can add more.
如果没有的话我可以添加更多。
This taste is spot on.
这个味道很到位。
tell me now,
现在告诉我，
why are you here
你为什么在这里
Come and visit me?
来拜访我吗？
Generally,
一般的，
Please give up the surgery.
请放弃手术。
Is Gu Yunzheng scared?
Is Gu Yunzheng scared?
So he sent a woman to beg for mercy?
所以他派了一个女人来求饶？
No, he doesn't know I'm here.
不，他不知道我在这里。
Generally speaking, there are many possibilities for your abnormal situation.
一般来说，您的异常情况有多种可能。
Surgery may not be necessary.
手术可能没有必要。
Generally,
一般的，
Miss Su is right.
苏小姐说得对。
I will accompany you to the General Hospital of Paris next month.
下个月我会陪你去巴黎中央医院。
They have the most advanced equipment in the world.
他们拥有世界上最先进的设备。
We can try again there.
我们可以在那里再试一次。
get away!
逃离！
It's been a year.
已经一年了。
I know
我知道
There's a time bomb inside me
我内心有一颗定时炸弹
But you just can't find it.
但你就是找不到它。
So, should I surrender?
那么，我应该投降吗？
What did Gu Yunzheng say?
顾云铮说什么？
He won't give up, just like you.
他不会放弃，就像你一样。
He said that in the face of disease,
他说，面对疾病，
Doctors and patients should be on the same team.
医生和病人 应该在同一个团队。
To Dr. Gu.
致顾博士。
You Chinese also say
你们中国人也说
No risk,
没有冒险，
Nothing was found.
一无所获。
Generally,
一般的，
How can I get you to give up surgery?
怎样才能让你 放弃手术？
Miss Su,
苏小姐，
Don't you want my surgery to be successful?
你不希望我的手术 成功吗？
Destroy enemies
消灭敌人
and live a long and healthy life.
并过上健康长寿的生活。
I could drink more
我可以多喝点酒
You can make more money.
你可以赚更多的钱。
I don't want money.
我不要钱。
I just hope Dr. Gu is safe.
我只希望顾医生平安。
Are you that money-grubbing Miss Su?
你就是那个贪财的苏小姐吗？
Dr. Gu is one of them
顾博士就是其中之一
The best neurosurgeon in China.
中国最好的神经外科医生。
Are you sure you want it?
你确定要吗
Ruining a doctor's career because of your stubbornness ?
为了你的固执而毁掉医生的职业生涯 ？
If he is really as good as you say
如果他真的 像你说的那么优秀的话
Why do you think he will lose?
你为什么认为他会输？
Because you are not actually sick.
因为你其实并没有病。
Do you know your condition?
你知道你的病情吗
In psychology, it’s called hypochondriasis?
心理学上叫疑病症？
Miss Su.
苏小姐。
You should seek psychological help,
你应该寻求心理帮助，
But not Dr. Gu.
但顾博士不是。
how dare you?
你怎么敢？
Get her out of here.
带她离开这里。
Average.
一般的。
Let me go.
让我走。
She was drunk.
她喝醉了。
She didn't mean to offend you.
她并不是有意冒犯你。
Miss Su, please stop talking.
苏小姐，请别再说了。
I'll walk you home.
我送你回家。
Average!
一般的！
Ask Dr. Gu to bring this crazy woman back.
叫顾医生 把这个疯女人带回来。
Yes, sir.
是的先生。
Hello?
你好？
Arrive at the General's Mansion.
来到将军府。
And take that crazy woman away.
并把那个疯女人带走。
She was drunk.
她喝醉了。
alright, I got it.
好吧，我明白了。
That idiot.
那个白痴。
That Dr. Gu,
那个顾博士，
Who is he to you?
他对你来说是谁？
he...
他...
he's mine...
他是我的...
Boy friend?
男朋友？
No.
不。
He is over there,
他在那边，
I'm here.
我在这里。
He is my teacher,
他是我的老师，
The person I admire most
我最敬佩的人
And the person I once wanted to be.
以及我曾经想成为的那个人。
Why do you say "once"?
为什么说“曾经”？
I...
我...
I don't have such good luck.
我就没有这么好的运气了。
what you look like now
你现在的样子
Reminds me of my mentor.
让我想起了我的导师。
She often sighs like this
她常常这样叹息
And complain to God.
并向上帝抱怨。
She enjoys playing with dice in the lab.
她喜欢在实验室里玩骰子。
Your mentor?
你的导师吗
Is there something wrong with her experiment too?
她的实验也有问题吗？
Because she always chooses
因为她始终选择
The path less traveled.
人迹罕至的路径。
Although she often fails,
虽然她经常失败，
Dr. Marta is still the most amazing doctor
玛塔医生仍然是 最了不起的医生
I once knew.
我曾经知道。
Dr. Martha?
玛莎博士？
the only one
唯一的那个
Who first attempted cell transplantation
谁首先尝试细胞移植
Is there a cure for Huntington's disease in the world?
世界上有治疗亨廷顿舞蹈病的方法吧？
How did you know?
你怎么知道的？
This is her experiment on a rare disease more than 20 years ago.
这是她 20多年前对一种罕见疾病的实验。
You may not have been born yet.
你可能还没有出生。
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
Thanks.
谢谢。
Dr. Elliot.
艾略特博士。
It's getting late.
天色已晚。
We should go back to the hospital. goodbye.
我们应该回医院。再见。
PhD. Gu.
博士。顾。
Why are you so determined to have this surgery?
为什么你这么坚决 要做这个手术？
Because, as a doctor,
因为，作为一名医生，
We should never ignore any signal
我们永远不应该忽视任何信号
from the patient's body.
来自病人的身体。
【Friendship Hospital】
【友谊医院】
Let's drink.
我们喝吧。
either you or me
要么你要么我
Be sure to get drunk.
一定要喝醉。
enough!
足够的！
Why you
为什么你
Going to the general's house for a drink tonight ?
今晚去将军家 喝酒？
It's all because you caused trouble
都是因为你惹了麻烦
It doesn't make me feel at ease either.
也不让我安心。
Who is causing trouble here?
到底是谁在这儿制造麻烦呢？
It's midnight now,
现在是午夜，
I have to pick you up at the general's house.
我得去 将军家接你。
Elliot.
艾略特.
Please help me intercede with the general.
请帮我向将军求情。
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
Can you stay away from Eliot?
你能远离艾略特吗？
Why? He is a good man.
为什么？他是一个好人。
Because you are my translator
因为你是我的翻译
Not Eliot's.
不是艾略特的。
Just rest here tonight
今晚就在这里休息吧
And clear your head.
并清醒你的头脑。
do not leave.
不要离开。
(these functions)
（这些功能）
(So)
（那么）
(normal.)
（普通的。）
Fang Mingfan.
Fang Mingfan.
what you up to?
你想做什么？
I didn't expect you to be like this.
我没想到你会这样。
What kind of person am I?
我是什么样的人？
your face,
你的脸，
Wipe it off.
把它擦掉。
Oh no!
不好了！
I didn't take my makeup off all night. This is a disaster.
我一晚上都没有卸妆。 这是一场灾难。
Even a hundred masks can't make up for it.
即使是一百个口罩也 无法弥补。
Paper.
纸。
Fang Mingfan, I'm warning you,
Fang Mingfan, I'm warning you,
do not tell anyone.
不要告诉任何人。
Tell anyone anything?
告诉任何人什么？
Don't tell anyone my makeup is ruined
别告诉任何人 我的妆毁了
also
也
I'm spending the night at your house.
我在你家过夜。
Who do I tell?
我要告诉谁？
Excellent...
出色地...
You can't tell anyone.
你不能告诉任何人。
Did you hear me?
你听到我说话了吗？
if you tell anyone,
如果你告诉任何人，
I won't let you go.
我不会放过你的。
OK
好的。
Don't laugh.
不要笑了。
Jiang.
蒋.
You are beautiful,
你很漂亮，
Even if your makeup is ruined.
即使你的妆容被毁了。
too early?
太早了？
Why are you still wearing yesterday's clothes?
你怎么还穿着昨天的衣服？
Aren't you the same?
你不也是吗？
I woke up early in the morning
我一大早就醒了
and went to exercise.
并去锻炼了。
I...
我...
I went there to make money
我是为了赚钱才去的
Negotiate business with major clients.
与大客户谈生意。
You've been drinking.
你一直在喝酒。
Who do you drink with?
你和谁一起喝酒？
【Friendship Hospital】
【友谊医院】
Have you found the direction of surgery?
找到 手术方向了吗？
Are you awake?
你清醒吗？
No more headaches?
不再头痛了吗？
Then let's go
那我们走吧
breakfast.
早餐。
Are you still in the mood for breakfast?
你还有心情吃早餐吗？
You drank a lot,
你喝了很多酒，
Why can't I eat?
为什么我不能吃东西？
I...
我...
I know you did it for me.
我知道你是为了我做的。
You don't want my reputation to be tarnished.
你不想让 我的名誉受到玷污。
But Su Wei'an,
But Su Wei'an,
Let me ask you something.
让我问你一件事。
why do you think
为什么你认为
I gave it to General Kouyate
我给了库亚特将军
Operation?
手术？
how could I know?
我怎么知道？
Is it because the general pointed a gun at you ?
是不是因为将军拿枪 指着你
Or because you want to compete
或者因为你想竞争
With Eliot?
与艾略特？
Su Wei'an,
Su Wei'an,
I'm a doctor.
我是个医生。
I had one reason for surgery.
我进行手术的理由只有一个。
The patient has indications for surgery
患者有手术指征
and required surgery.
并且需要手术。
Why can't you believe me?
你为什么不能相信我？
I trust you.
我相信你。
But I've been through all the medical cases
但我经历了所有的医疗案例
The image is not clear,
图像不清晰，
None resembled the general's situation.
没有一个 与将军的情况相似。
So, you gave up?
所以，你放弃了？
Does Huaren Medical University only teach you?
华仁医科大学 只教你吗
How can you give up?
你怎么能放弃呢？
What?
什么？
She is indeed a silly girl.
确实是个傻姑娘。
No wonder you are an undergraduate.
难怪你是个本科生。
I'm not an undergraduate.
我不是本科生。
I have a bachelor's degree.
我有学士学位。
Bachelor's degree?
学士学位？
In college classes,
在大学课堂上，
Mr. Gu taught you something.
顾先生教了你一些东西。
But I guess you forgot all about it.
但我猜你全忘了。
I really do not know
我真的不知道
How did you get your bachelor's degree.
你是如何获得学士学位的。
everyone,
每个人，
today,
今天，
We need to learn the diagnostic thinking of brain tumors
我们要学习 脑肿瘤的诊断思维
Combined with practice.
结合实践。
very clear
非常清楚
We can't see obvious lesions
我们看不到明显的病变
CT from patient.
来自患者的 CT。
Then, let's check out the MRI.
然后，让我们检查一下 MRI。
We can clearly see some lesions
我们可以清楚地看到一些病变
On the patient's brainstem, right?
在病人的脑干上，是吗？
gentlemen. Gu,
先生。顾,
If the lesion still cannot be seen on MRI,
如果 MRI 仍然看不到病变，
What should the doctor do?
医生应该做什么？
He should do clinical follow-up
他应该做临床随访
Judging the development of the disease based on experience ,
根据经验判断 疾病的发展，
and confirm the follow-up intervals.
并确认随访的时间间隔。
So what must doctors believe,
那么医生必须相信什么，
Clinical experience or precision instruments?
临床经验， 还是精密仪器？
When a doctor cures a disease,
当医生治愈疾病时，
Guidance is his rule,
指导是他的准则，
Knowledge is his foundation,
知识是他的基础，
Experience is his tool.
经验是他的工具。
With rigorous examination results,
凭借严格的考试成绩，
Doctors can figure it out
医生可以弄清楚
Detailed description of lesions quickly and accurately
快速准确地详细描述病变
To avoid delays or misdiagnosis.
以免延误或误诊。
So, I want you all to keep that in mind.
所以，我希望大家牢记这一点。
only by using instruments
只能通过使用仪器
and develop their own clinical thinking
并发展 自己的临床思维
Can you truly be responsible for your patients?
你能 真正对病人负责吗？
you remember me.
你记得我。
So you keep asking questions in class
所以你在课堂上不断提问
Just so I can remember you?
只是为了让我记住你？
of course not.
当然不是。
This is the question you asked,
这是你问的问题，
But you forgot the answer.
但你忘记了答案。
Use instruments.
使用仪器。
but...
但...
Why are you sure you can see the abnormality within a month?
为什么你确定 一个月就能看到异常？
What is the patient's walking problem?
患者的行走问题是什么？
He swaggers,
他大摇大摆，
swaying,
摇曳,
And shuffle the cards.
并洗牌。
What disease do these symptoms indicate?
这些症状预示着什么疾病呢？
He looks like a drunkard,
一副酒鬼的样子，
Leg weakness,
腿部无力，
and cerebellar ataxia.
和小脑性共济失调。
Is there anything wrong with his speech?
他说话有什么问题吗？
He has slurred speech
他口齿不清
and stammered.
并结结巴巴。
Dysarthria.
构音障碍。
What is he complaining about?
他抱怨什么？
While you're downstairs,
当你在楼下的时候，
I could shoot your head off.
我可以开枪打掉你的头。
But now, I can't.
但现在，我不能了。
His skills declined.
他的技能下降了。
Decreased flexibility of limbs.
四肢灵活性下降。
so?
所以？
Therefore, the disease may be in...
所以，病变可能在...
in his brainstem.
在他的脑干中。
not bad.
还不错。
You haven't completely forgotten it.
你还没有完全忘记它。
Today's imaging technology is very advanced.
现在的成像技术 已经很先进了。
Why can’t we see the lesions?
为什么我们看不到病变？
Maybe it's in a weird position.
也许它处于一个奇怪的位置。
Or maybe it's the initial stages.
或者也许这是初始阶段。
But anyway,
但不管怎么说，
doctors like us
像我们这样的医生
Don’t ignore every tiny signal
不能忽视每一个微小的信号
from the patient's body.
来自病人的身体。
【Friendship Hospital】
【友谊医院】
[One month later] General,
[一个月后] 将军，
MRI shows some abnormalities
MRI 显示一些异常
In your brainstem.
在你的脑干中。
Next,
下一个，
Trust Dr. Gu.
相信顾博士。
Please trust him.
请相信他。
Knock it off?
打掉它吗？
What are you doing here?
你们在这儿做什么？
On behalf of the local health board,
我代表 当地卫生健康委员会，
I will supervise the entire operation.
整个手术过程我都会监督。
MRI shows
MRI 表明
Some abnormalities in the brainstem.
脑干的一些异常。
Next,
下一个，
Chinese doctors will demonstrate their superb medical skills.
中国医生将展现 高超的医术。
they are.
他们是。
Gu Yunzheng is so young.
Gu Yunzheng is so young.
How dare he do brain stem surgery?
他怎么敢做脑干手术？
you are wrong.
你错了。
We should believe Dr. Gu.
我们应该相信顾博士。
【Friendship Hospital】
【友谊医院】
Average!
一般的！
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
I'll go in now. Wherever the general is, I will be there.
我这就进去。 将军在哪里我就在哪里。
He said he would stay wherever the general was.
他说将军在哪里他就留在哪里。
Let him in.
让他进来。
The doctor said we can go in.
医生说可以进去了。
but you must obey
但你必须服从
Sterility rules.
无菌规则。
follow me.
跟我来。
boss,
老板，
Wherever you go, I will go.
无论你去哪里，我都会去。
I will even die with you.
我什至会和你一起死。
No one dies unless your hands tremble.
除非你的手发抖，否则没有人会死。
you...
你...
Die with you?
和你一起死？
Then my life would be tragic.
那我的人生就悲剧了。
It has been a long time.
已经很久了。
Can he succeed?
他能成功吗？
I told you.
我告诉你了。
He couldn't have brainstem surgery.
他不能做脑干手术。
PhD. Gu
博士。顾
Persistence risked the general's life.
坚持冒着将军的生命危险。
before irreparable damage is caused,
在造成不可挽回的损害之前，
It's not too late to close his skull.
现在关闭他的头骨还为时不晚。
The operation is not over yet.
手术还没有结束。
Don't jump to conclusions.
不要急于下结论。
Blood pressure is falling.
血压正在下降。
PhD. Gu,
博士。顾,
Put down the scalpel immediately.
立即放下手术刀。
Otherwise I will hold you accountable
不然我会追究你的责任
I represent the Board of Health.
我代表卫生健康委员会。
Leave it all to Dr. Elliot.
一切都交给艾略特博士吧。
Go away. Otherwise I will kill you.
走开。不然我就杀了你。
Get out now!
赶紧出去吧！
You are not approaching Dr. Gu
你不是在接近顾博士
Unless I die.
除非我死了。
No one can stop Dr. Gu's surgery.
没有人能阻止顾医生的手术。
No one is allowed to disturb the surgeon.
任何人不得打扰外科医生。
Miss Su,
苏小姐，
You are just a translator.
你只是一个翻译。
You are not qualified to comment on surgery.
你没有资格 对手术发表评论。
It's not too late to stop it.
现在阻止还为时不晚。
I graduated with a major in clinical medicine
我是临床医学专业毕业的
from Huaren Medical University.
来自华仁医科大学。
I have a medical certificate.
我有医师资格证。
Whatever I say, I will answer.
无论我说什么，我都会回答。
If something happens to the general
如果将军出了什么事
None of you can survive.
你们没有一个人能活下去。
The lesion was located in his medulla.
病变位于他的髓质。
It's incredible.
太不可思议了。
Do you understand?
你们明白了吗？
I think you should consider
我认为你应该考虑
How to apologize to Dr. Gu later.
稍后如何向顾医生道歉。
Let go of values.
放下价值观。
Why isn't the general awake yet?
将军怎么还不醒？
It's been so long since the surgery.
手术已经结束这么久了。
You are not allowed to leave!
你不许走！
You quack!
你嘎嘎！
The general won't wake up so soon.
将军不会这么快醒来。
But the operation was very successful.
但手术非常成功。
Dr. Gu did a perfect job.
顾博士做得非常完美。
The lesion was also perfectly resected.
病变也被完美切除。
I underestimated him.
我低估了他。
you are wrong?
你错了？
Dr. Elliot.
艾略特博士。
Now,
现在，
You promised.
你保证过。
as you said,
如你所说，
Dr. Gu is a very good doctor.
顾医生是一位非常优秀的医生。
I will apologize to him
我会向他道歉
For everything I do.
对于我所做的一切。
PhD. Gu,
博士。顾,
sorry.
对不起。
You're just worried about the general.
你只是担心将军而已。
When we get the biopsy results
当我们得到活检结果后
We will keep you posted.
我们会及时通知您。
Thanks.
谢谢。
what do I do?
我该怎么办？
What should we do now?
现在怎么办？
In the operating room,
在手术室里，
You risked your life to protect me again.
你冒着生命危险 再次保护我。
tell me.
告诉我。
When I owed a girl my life twice
当我两次欠一个女孩一条命时
How can I repay her?
我该如何报答她呢？
I don't. do not think too much.
我没有。别想太多。
You protected me from the gun.
你在枪前保护了我。
I have to think too much.
我得想太多了。
Now,
现在，
You tell the health commission representative
你告诉卫健委代表
I am your idol
我是你的偶像
You will die for me.
你会为我而死。
(Idol?)
（偶像？）
I see.
我明白。
I am very touched.
我很感动。
When have I ever said such a thing?
我什么时候说过这样的话了？
Don't pretend you understand.
别假装你明白。
you have not?
你没有？
Maybe I heard what you were saying.
也许我听到了你的心声。
Su Wei'an.
Su Wei'an.
no way
绝不
Making fun of your life again.
再次拿你的生活开玩笑。
You can't risk your life.
你不能拿自己的生命冒险。
Not even for me.
甚至对我来说也不行。
while you are still alive,
当你还活着的时候，
You can save more people.
你可以拯救更多的人。
It's worth trading my life for yours.
用我的生命换你的生命是值得的。
I told you.
我告诉你了。
Never say this again.
永远不要再说这句话了。
no one's life
没有人的生活
Can be more valuable than others.
可以 比别人的更有价值。
Wait a moment.
等一下。
What? Do you know you are wrong?
什么？知道自己错了吗？
Didn't you just say
你刚才不是说
Don't you know how to repay me?
你不知道如何报答我吗？
Give me a raise
给我加薪吧
Su Wei'an!
Su Wei'an!
Money is better than death, isn't it?
金钱胜过死亡，不是吗？
do you know that person
你认识那个人吗
Didn't you even release the safety lock?
连安全锁都没有松开？
♪Move the hands of the clock at night♪
♪夜晚移动时钟的指针♪
♪Noise replaced silence♪
♪喧闹取代了寂静♪
♪We act out the script of an encounter♪
♪我们演绎一场邂逅的剧本♪
♪The rainbow is embedded in the night♪
♪彩虹镶嵌在夜色中♪
♪And the wind blowing across the desert♪
♪还有吹过沙漠的风♪
♪Everyone has been our witness♪
♪都曾经是我们的见证者♪
♪Who doesn’t get lost in the vastness♪
♪谁不迷失在茫茫茫茫之中♪
♪Looking for a glimmer of hope? ♪
♪寻找一线生机？♪
♪Trapped in this city called destiny♪
♪被困在这座名为命运的城市♪
♪Still chasing stars♪
♪仍然追星♪
♪Don't worry, my lost loved ones♪
♪别担心，我失去的亲人♪
♪Your lonely soul is warmed by wine♪
♪你孤独的灵魂因酒而温暖♪
♪Let me hug your wounds♪
♪让我拥抱你的伤口♪
♪You shine like a star♪
♪你像星星一样闪耀♪
♪Flickers in the loneliest moments♪
♪在最孤独的时候闪烁♪
♪Move the hands of the clock at night♪
♪夜晚移动时钟的指针♪
♪Noise replaced silence♪
♪喧闹取代了寂静♪
♪We act out the script of an encounter♪
♪我们演绎一场邂逅的剧本♪
♪The rainbow is embedded in the night♪
♪彩虹镶嵌在夜色中♪
♪And the wind blowing across the desert♪
♪还有吹过沙漠的风♪
♪Everyone has been our witness♪
♪都曾经是我们的见证者♪
♪Who doesn’t get lost in the vastness♪
♪谁不迷失在茫茫茫茫之中♪
♪Looking for a glimmer of hope? ♪
♪寻找一线生机？♪
♪Trapped in this city called destiny♪
♪被困在这座名为命运的城市♪
♪Still chasing stars♪
♪仍然追星♪
♪Don't worry, my lost loved ones♪
♪别担心，我失去的亲人♪
♪Your lonely soul is warmed by wine♪
♪你孤独的灵魂因酒而温暖♪
♪Let me hug your wounds♪
♪让我拥抱你的伤口♪
♪You shine like a star♪
♪你像星星一样闪耀♪
♪Flickers in the loneliest moments♪
♪在最孤独的时候闪烁♪